<entry identifier="p003r_a1">

<folio number="003r"
    url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f11.image"/>
    <annotations>
        <annotation
            url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwJi-u8sfkVDUWd6WXF6RzExYnc"
            title="Imitation Coral, fol. 3r (Chessa)"/>
    </annotations>
    

<heading>Imitation <material>coral</material></heading>

<block>
<activity type="imitation coral"/>
<purpose type="making"/>
+

One must first make the <material_format>branches from <material>wood</material></material_format> or take a <material_format>fantastical <plant>thorn</plant> branch</material_format>, then melt a <unit>pound</unit> of the <material_format>best possible clear <material>pine resin</material></material_format> and add one <unit>ounce</unit> of <material_format>finely ground <material>vermilion</material></material_format> together with <material>walnut oil</material>, and if you add a little <material>Venice lake</material> the color will be all the more vivid, and stir all together into the <material>resin</material>, molten over a <tool>charcoal fire</tool>, not over an open flame, lest it catch fire. Then dip in your <material>branches</material> with a swirling motion. And should there remain any filaments, turn the branch over the heat of the <material>charcoal</material>.</block>


<purpose type="observation">
    
<block position="left-top"><material>Colophony</material> is nothing other than <material>resin</material> that has been cooked again. To do it well, you take a <material_format><material>lead</material>ed pot</material_format> and melt the <material>resin</material>, boiling it over the <tool>brazier</tool> for a good <time>hour</time> until it appears not thick but clear and liquid like <material>water</material> and it easily runs as a thread off the end of a <tool>stick</tool>, which you use to crush and test it. Then pour it through a <material>coarse canvas</material> or <material>tammy cloth</material> so that it falls into the <material_format>strongest <material>vinegar</material> you can find</material_format>, because the <material>vinegar</material> makes it strong and makes it less brittle. Repeat this two or three times and it will be fine and well purified. To imitate your <material>coral</material>, you can mix a <unit>fourth part</unit> of <material>mastic</material> with your <material_format>purified <material>resin</material></material_format> to make it more solid and finer, and if you should use just one <unit>drop</unit> of <material>mastic</material>, it would be all the better, but it would take too long.</block>

<block position="top-middle"><material>Coral</material> made of <material><color>red</color> enamel</material> withstands filing and polishing.</block>

<block position="right-top">It is made like <material>cement</material>, which is stronger when mixed with <material>crushed glass</material> rather than with <material>brick</material>. In the same way, together with the <material>vermilion</material>, one mixes in <material_format><material>opaque <color>red</color> enamel</material>, finely ground</material_format>. It is the same way with all <material>enamel colors</material>.
</block>

<block position="left-middle"><material>Sulfur</material> and <material>vermilion</material> have the same effect.</block>
</purpose>   

</entry>
