<entry identifier="p004r_1">
    <folio number="004r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f13.image"/>
    <heading>
        <material_format><material>Lavender spike oil</material> varnish</material_format>
    </heading>
    <block>
        <activity type="varnish"/>
        <purpose type="making"> One must heat <material>lavender spike oil</material> and, as it
            begins to simmer, put in <material_format>powdered <material>sandarac
                gum</material></material_format> so that it soon melts. And stir continuously over a
                <tool>charcoal fire</tool> until the <material>sandarac</material> is well melted,
            which you will know by taking a little of the said varnish on a <tool>plate</tool> and,
            if it is fat enough when you handle it with a <tool>finger</tool>, it is ready. And for
                <unit>one pound</unit> of <material>lavender spike oil</material>, you should put
                <unit>five ounces</unit> of <material_format>ground
                <material>sandarac</material></material_format>.</purpose>
        <purpose type="observation"> Some only put in <unit>four ounces</unit> but this is not as
            good, nor as fat. The former dries promptly. To avoid the trouble of polishing their
                <material>ebony</material>, <profession>framemakers</profession> varnish it with
            this. So do <profession>guitarmakers</profession>. This varnish is not as fitting for
            paintings as <material_format>fine <material>turpentine</material>
                varnish</material_format>, though it is good for the paintings' moldings. When
                    <material_format><material>linseed</material> varnish</material_format> was in
            use, one would not commonly varnish the landscape of a painting because it would turn
            the landscape yellow. But with
                    <material_format><material>turpentine</material> varnish</material_format> one
            varnishes everywhere. Instead of <material>sandarac</material>, you can add to it
                <material_format>pulverized <material>mastic</material></material_format>
            <unit>drop</unit> by <unit>drop</unit> or otherwise, and it will dry more
            quickly.</purpose>
        <purpose type="advice"> If you want to varnish <material>plaster</material> or a wall, first
            put on your <material><foreign language="french">colle de retaille</foreign></material>,
            very hot, because if cold it would not penetrate the wall at all. And when you would
            have put your varnish on, it would come off.</purpose>
    </block>
    <block position="left-top">
        <purpose type="observation">
            <material_format><material>Aspic oil</material> varnish</material_format> is not as apt
            for colors as that of <material>turpentine</material>, because <material>aspic
                oil</material> eats the colors, since it is too penetrating.</purpose>
    </block>
</entry>
