<entry identifier="p005r_a2">
    <folio number="005r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f15.image"/>

    <heading>Concave mirrors</heading>

    <block>
        <activity type="practical optics"/>
        <purpose type="observation"/>A concave mirror shaped in the aforesaid form produces an
        endless number of illusions which seem like magic. If one wants to see oneself from behind,
        you have to place the concave mirror on the ground on its foot, at a slant, and then look at
        it one step further. But if you look at it from a closer position, it shows you the right
        way up but with the face quite large and the hairs of your beard as thick as </block>

    <folio number="005v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f16.image"/>

    <block>
        <activity type="practical optics"/>
        <purpose type="observation"/>a string and will reflect a nipple as large as a plate, and
        women can see the secret places they do not want to show to surgeons. It projects the
        reflection outwards, and if you touch with your finger the eye of the reflection, another
        finger will come against yours.
        <!--is there a block break here? PDF suggests as much; folio not really-->You will be able
        to provide light at night for someone quite far away, if you set the concave mirror behind a
        candle placed on a window sill. You will be able to read and write quite far from the candle
        if you set it behind the candle and turn the concave face towards you. If you put the mirror
        at the far end of a table with a candle on it, it will reflect two lights on the table for
        you.
        <!--is there anything worth encoding in the following observation? materials? tools?-->To
        see what is happening in a street, shut the window, or the more you can shut the better,
        make a hole in the bottom pane, the size of your little finger, perfectly round all the way
        through. Then apply a sheet of paper onto the window and let the middle of the sheet be over
        the hole. Pierce the sheet in the same place as the hole and of the same size. Then turn the
        concave face of the mirror towards the hole, and anyone passing by in the street will be
        reflected on the sheet of paper. Do the same with the pierced door of a closed room. You can
        make wavy mirrors and triangular ones, such as are described by <name type="personal">Ptolemy</name> and
            <name type="personal">Archimedes</name>. The concave sort can also set fire to
            <material>straw</material> or light a candle from afar, using the <tool>sun</tool>. By
        reverberating fire too, it can provide warmth. </block>
</entry>
