<entry identifier="p012v_3">
    <folio number="012v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f30.image"/>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <purpose type="observation"/>
    <activity type="polishing"/>
    <activity type="engraving"/>
    <heading>To <color>white</color>n <material>enilanroc</material></heading>

    <block>Some believe the ceruse-color crust that is on top to be natural. Others say that it is a
        lost secret of ancient <profession>lapidaries</profession>. Others say that it is
            <material>enamel</material> that has been reheated. And, from this crust, one can form
        multiple ciphers, letters, circles and other bizarre motifs. As to the means, I proceeded
        thus: I once wanted to add a layer of <material>arsenic</material> ground on
            <material>marble</material>. However, I did the experiment without it, and I put the
        above mentioned thing, <material>enilanroc</material>, in a <tool>small
                <material>iron</material> casket</tool> on the <tool>fire</tool> of my
                <tool><profession>goldsmith</profession>'s forge</tool> with three or four
            <material_format>small half-burnt <material>coal</material>s</material_format> and blew
        on it only with my <tool>mouth</tool>. However, the thing caught fire and became all <color>white</color>,
        not only on its surface but also inside. And then I let it cool on its own near the <tool>fire</tool>,
        since otherwise, exposing it suddenly to cold air, it would have cracked. While it was all
        <color>white</color>, I passed it through my <tool><material>lead</material> wheel</tool> and I found it to be as hard as it was before. And
        after scraping off a little of the <color>white</color>, I found it to be of <color>a clear fleshy tone</color>. Finally,
        I polished it and observed that it took quite a beautiful polish luster and that it could
        compare with a quite beautiful <material>agate</material> for the purpose of engraving it with some beautiful
        face and applying it to a table of</block>

    <folio number="013r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f31.image"/>

    <block> <material>agate</material> of various colors. But because this overall <color>white</color>ness did not correspond with the
        <color>white</color> crust on the surface that I was seeking, leaving the rest of the thing its <color>natural
            color</color>, I made a hole in a <tool><material>brick</material></tool>, precisely the same size as the object, and put it inside.
        Then I heated two <tool><profession>glassmaker</profession>'s soldering iron</tool>s until they became <color>red</color> hot and, when they were
        <color>red</color> hot, I applied them one after the other onto the surface of the object until I got the
        <color>white</color> crust I was looking for, on which I made the drawing that I wanted, revealing the <color>red</color>
        background, with a <tool>diamond point</tool>, and I polished it with <tool>hog bristles</tool> and <tool><material>tripoli</material></tool>. I don't
            know if it would be better to reheat it under <tool><material_format>hot <material>ashes</material></material_format></tool>, and if it would be good to encase
            it in <tool><material>alabaster</material></tool>, which is quite cold, as I did in the <tool><material>brick</material></tool>. 
    </block>
</entry>
