<entry identifier="p014r_1">
    <folio number="0114r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f31.item"/>
    <purpose type="observation"/>
    <activity type="construction"/>
    <heading>For <material_format><material>earth</material> walls</material_format> and rustic
        construction</heading>

    <block><animal>Swallows</animal> have taught us this craft by building their nests out of
            <material>mud</material> mingled with wisps and bits of
            <material><plant>hay</plant></material> or <material><plant>straw</plant></material> to
        make it bond. Therefore, in places where <material>stones</material> and
            <material>bricks</material> are lacking, one can use <material>earth</material> to make
        walls thin and thick. The best for this is <material_format>light
            <material>earth</material></material_format>, which does not form clumps when plowed, or
        better, that which in some way mingled with <material>arene</material>, because it can be
        most easily beaten and tamped down. It is true that it needs to be dampened and cut into
        clumps with a <tool>ditch-spade</tool>, and put and placed in this <tool>form</tool>. This
        one lasts more and does not require that much effort, and dryness doesn't make it split or
        crack. However, since such kinds of <material>earth</material> are not found everywhere,
        those who live on good and fertile land, after drawing the width and length of their
        foundations with a <tool>rope</tool>, drive in <tool>long poles and rafters</tool> along the
        edges on each side to support <tool>boards</tool> between which they throw the
            <material>earth</material>, making each layer about <unit>one foot</unit> thick,
        interspersed with <material_format>S.S.S-shaped branches of
                <material><plant>heather</plant></material></material_format> or similar things,
        then they tamp it down and beat it with <tool>beaters of three different forms</tool>. One
        is called the <tool>mall</tool>, which has a triangular form like A, and this is used
        firstly to tamp down the <material>earth</material>. Then one uses another made of
            <tool>pointed <material>woodblocks</material> fitted onto a thick stick</tool>, and this
        one is used to properly press the <material>earth</material> at the wall’s ends and edges
        where they adhere to the <tool>boards</tool>, and is called [blank]. The other one is called
        the <tool>bat</tool> and is used to flatten and beat the <material>earth</material> for the
        last time, as shown in C. Then one makes another layer of <material>earth</material> and
                <material><plant>heather</plant></material> and beats as has been said, and
        continues thus until completing the wall, which is covered with
                <material><plant>heather</plant></material> and then with
        <material>earth</material>. Some intersperse the said wall with rows of
            <material>bricks</material>. They also make walls with a sloped foot, adding width to
        the foundations according to how high they want to build the wall. When it is old it
            <color>white</color>ns, showing that it has <material>saltpeter</material> in it. Which
        is why, when they fall down, <profession>gunpowder</profession> makers profit from
        them.</block>

    <figure identifier="fig_p014r_1" position="left-bottom"
        url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5b2lVN19SU1Z6UkU"/>

</entry>
