<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p039v_a3">

    <folio number="039v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f84.image"/>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <purpose type="application"/>
    <purpose type="observation"/>

    <annotations>
        <annotation title="Tracing a history on glass"
            url="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1hadGQunGoh9R6eJUndm-5MxRcoIi_r95EOG-ZqizP4Y/edit"
        />
    </annotations>

    <heading>Tracing a history on glass</heading>

    <block>If you want to trace a history in intaglio on <material>glass</material>, you can do so
        in different ways. Place your glass pane on, as thin as possible, over the printed history,
        &amp; having cleaned the glass well with <material>lye</material> &amp;
            <material>ashes</material> so that it is not at all greasy, trace over the lines visible
        to you with oily black or scales black with a <tool>pinceau</tool>, if you want to paint
        with colors in the manner of glaziers, who spread a wash of scales black all over their
        glass pane &amp; then scratch &amp; uncover what they want to coat with color, leaving that
        which is necessary for shading. But if you want to make gilt histories on glass with a
        background of colors, which imitates the basse-taille of goldsmiths, gild the whole glass
        pane with <material>gum water</material> or <material>garlic juice</material> or
            <material>fig-tree milk</material>. Then moisten your printed history with two wet
            <tool>linen cloths</tool> &amp; lay it down on the gilt glass. Then with a
            <tool>pin</tool> mounted on a small <tool>stick</tool>, follow the lines of your history
        as if you wished to pounce it, &amp; thus you shall vividly trace it on the gilding of the
        glass. &amp; next you shall uncover the background &amp; what needs to be empty with a quite
        pointy steel <tool>awl</tool>, &amp; and neatly follow once more the lines &amp; accomplish
        your work &amp; fashion your faces &amp; flesh tones in <material>pounded silver</material>;
        then fill the background with <material>azur d’esmail</material> or
            <material>verdigris</material> or <material>fine laque platte</material>, tempered with
        clear <material>turpentine</material>, mixed with a little <material>larme de
            mastic</material> if you want the colors to be more unified &amp; not to run. Next,
        apply on the back of the glass &amp; over the colors a white <tool>tin sheet</tool>. And
        once this is dry, you can cover the tin sheet of with color to hide your secret. The tin
        sheet gives light to the colors. Thus you will be able to paint without being</block>
    <folio number="040r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f85.image"/>
    <block>being at all expert in painting. If your glass pane is bulging as if taken from the belly
        of a jar, it will show better. When you apply your turpentine colors to your glass panes,
        first place them on a <tool>hot tile</tool> &amp;, once they are hot, spread your colors
        &amp; leave it a while on the tile, then lay down your tin sheet.</block>
</entry>
