<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p045r_1">

    <folio number="045r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f95.image"/>
    <purpose type="advice"/>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <purpose type="observation"/>
    
    <heading>Loading a pellet arquebus</heading>
    
    <figure number="fig_p045r_1" position="top-center"
        url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bkhmQklfNHJoRnc"/>

    <block>It is necessary to make a <tool>wooden pipe</tool> 4 or 5 fingers wide that is perfectly
        hollow, according to the open end of your barrel, of the form represented in A. Then, having
        cut some <material>paper</material>, which has to be as strong as that of large printed
        books, in the form indicated in D and as wide as you want your cartridge to be long, wrap
        the paper around the <tool>baton</tool> B and at the top, where the pointed tip F will be
        around the aforementioned paper, and the cartridge will be formed. But, in order to make the
        bottom more uniform, put it into <tool>pipe</tool> A, then introduce baton B and, in the
        other end of the pipe, which is marked G, insert baton C and pack so as to compact and press
        the folded tip of your cartridge, then take it out, and the charge in this, put three or
        four drageons or <material>larmes</material>. Then, with a <tool>punch</tool>, marked E, of
        the same caliber of your arquebus or pistol, punch round pieces on cardboard or felt or
        waxed cloth, and put this round piece into your cartridge, and push it until the drageons
        with the baton B, the more drageons, 3 or 4, then a round piece. And continue like that
        until the cartridge is full, the put it into the <tool>arquebus</tool>. If you want your
        pellet to scatter earlier, make round pieces out of paper. If you want it to reach further
        without scattering, make the piece out of <material>cardboard</material>. If you want it to
        reach even further, make the round piece out of <material>waxed cloth</material>, or either
        of <material>leather</material> or <material>felt</material>, and a piece of waxed cloth on
        the top. And if you make the cartridge in part with waxed cloth or <material>waxed
            paper</material>, it will reach one hundred paces and will make a big hole, and the
        pellet, barely scattering, will produce a big opening. But if you make your cartridge with
        waxed cloth or a material stronger than paper, it cannot be so long, with the cardboard tip
        being like in D, because it is enough if it wrapped around twice. In such a way, the pellet
        barely scatters and makes a big hole in porte-corps armor or others.</block>
</entry>
