<entry identifier="p048v_a2">
    <folio number="048v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f102.image"/>
    <purpose type="observation"/>

    <heading>
        <material>Lead tin</material>
    </heading>

    <block>They crack if they are often melted again and thicken and burn, so that even if a salmon
        is made, the <material>tin</material> becomes thick at the bottom if it is not stirred often
        during casting. It is better for casting to melt some <material>lead</material> and some
            <material>tin</material> and to renew it each time. The <material>antimony</material>
        makes them breakable, the <material>iced tin</material> makes them whiter. Pewterers mix a
        pound of <material>iced tin</material> with a quintal of <material>fine tin</material> and
        two and a half or three pounds of <material>red, mild cauldron copper</material>, which is
        better than <material>latten.</material> There is <material>fine and mild tin</material> and
            <material>sour tin</material>. Pewterers cast the sour as grills to sell it better. They
        go better and more cleanly in <material>stone</material> moulds than in
            <material>copper</material> molds because <material>copper</material> is fat and draws
        the <material>mild tin</material> when heated. Or when casting a large work, three quarts of
            <material>lead</material> with one pound of <material>mild tin</material> produces a
        very liquid mixture which is appropriate for casting and is as shiny as a mirror. Laxunge
            <material>glass</material> lightens them. All things that lighten
            <material>metals</material> a lot and remove their thickness and natural density and
        make them as liquid as water make them appropriate for casting because their thickness stops
        them from flowing. The <material>mild tin</material> is more even than the <material>sour
            tin</material>, which is whiter and seems to have been polished like a mirror.</block>

    <block position="left-bottom"> To properly alloy the <material>tin</material> and the
            <material>lead</material>, you have to melt them together, Then, mix them together a
        little bit at a time and throw it often on a <material>marble tile</material>. And when it
        is going well, you will see it becoming unified and shining as if it were burnished. Because
        sometimes it becomes spotted due to too much <material>lead</material> and sometimes due to
        too much <material>tin</material>. There is some <material>tin</material> allied with more
            <material>lead</material>. Ordinary <material>tin</material> is allied with some
            <material>lead</material>.</block>

</entry>
