<entry identifier="p051r_a2">
    <folio number="051r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f107.image"/>
    <purpose type="advice"/>

    <heading>Cutters of printing plates</heading>

    <block>To clean the <material>copper</material> plates or to have used ones print better, boil
        them for four or five hours in a good <material>detergent</material> with quite used
            <material>laundry water</material>. Then make your <material>ink</material> with some
            <material>linseed oil</material> instead of <material>walnut oil</material> and press
        with the rollers. The <material>copper</material> plates are ready sooner than the
            <material>wood</material> ones, but they are not so clean to print promptly. The
            <material>wood</material> ones are tedious but would have sooner printed twenty sheets
        against two [sheets] of the other. To print with <material>wood</material>, the secret is
        firstly to poach, that is to say to lay the transferred pattern or drawn piece down on the
            <material>wood</material> plank and to make sure that the drawn side is stuck to the
            <material>wood</material>. Once dry, you will gently rub with a moist
            <material>handkerchief</material> the reverse side of the <material>paper</material>
        which, by being rubbed, will become so fine that what will remain will almost only be the
        drawn part, which, after, one should trace while cutting the pattern. You could do that to
        ornamented <material>glass</material> and <material>glass</material> layered with
            <material>black</material> cut pieces, to then scrape and layer your
            <material>colors</material> on the uncovered [side]. To make <material>ink</material>
        for <material>copper</material> plates</block>

    <folio number="051v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f108.image"/>

    <block>which is different from the printers' one, you have to boil for a long time some
            <material>walnut oil</material> or, even better, some <material>linseed oil</material>,
        and after boiling for a long time, you will add <material>garlic</material> cloves and
            <material>bread</material> crusts to skim them and leave again to boil on big fire, then
        eventually you will add a measure of <material>lampblack</material> that you would have
        ground with some <material>oil</material> previously on the <material>marble</material>. And
        lastly you will mix everything and until you see that the plate prints well. And when you
        will have spread the <material>ink</material>, dry the plate with a white sheet of
            <material>paper</material> and do that until the <material>paper</material> looks clean
        and then print. If you dry the plates with a <material>cloth</material>, it would remove the
            <material>ink</material> off. <material>Linseed oil</material> gets thicker while
        boiling and becomes similar to a varnish and risks catching fire as soon as you boil it, so
        make sure that when you boil it, it is in an open space or where the flame cannot damage
        anything. Some burn some <material>scale</material> until it turns black and grind it with
        some non-boiled <material>linseed oil</material> or <material>walnut oil</material> that
        some consider to be better. This black is beautiful but the <material>lamp smoke</material>
        one is blacker. When you want to print, take with your finger's end and reasonably spread
        some of the said <material>black</material> all over the plate previously cleaned with some
            <material>detergent</material> as said, then, rub it with a white sheet of
            <material>paper</material> until the paper is completely white and do not touch it with
        your bare hand but with a <material>paper</material> applied on it. And after cleaning the
        plate perfectly, rub again the sides and edges with a folded sheet of
            <material>paper</material>. Then, have [available] a small even table and on it a piece
        of <material>felt</material>, then a few sheets of <material>paper</material> and eventually
        the one you want to print on, moistened between two humid <material>napkins</material>. And
        on this sheet of <material>paper</material>, put your sheet then some more
            <material>paper</material>, and at least another piece of <material>felt</material>.
        Then put it through the rollers and you can print a dozen pieces consecutively while always
        charging the plate with <material>ink</material> and cleaning it as you did. But if you stop
        printing, the rest of the <material>ink</material> will dry out in the plate's lines and so
        you will have to let it boil in <material>detergent</material> or
        <material>urine</material>, as said, to clean it. The rollers must not be too loose.</block>

</entry>
