<entry identifier="p052r_1">
  <folio number="052r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f109.item"/>
  <purpose type="observation"/>
  <purpose type="advice"/>

  <heading>The Work done in Algiers</heading>

  <block>Have a <animal>colt</animal> of three of four years and feed it on
      <material>barley</material> and <material>straw</material> cut in the same way as that which
    they use to feed horses in <place>Spain</place>. Let it drink <material>water</material> from a
    good fountain or river <material>water</material>. I do not know if it would be good sometimes
    to let him drink the <material>water</material> of <material>sulfur</material> springs, and to
    sometimes give him <material>fenugreek</material> or other hot foods, for the intention of the
    worker is to use the heat of his <material>manure</material>, and the climate here is cooler
    than that of Algiers. Keep it in a warm place and use it and make sure it loses none of its
      <material>manure</material> or <material>urine</material>, of which you will make a mass or
    two so that while one cools the other will keep its heat and be suitable to continue. Also have
    a large flask as thick as possible, one finger thick if it can be so made, and with a capacity
    of one pitcher or <material>clay</material> jug, and around the feast of St John place a dozen
    and a half <material>chicken eggs</material>, that is to say, the <material>egg</material>
    without the <material>egg white</material> and the <material>germ</material>. Others say sixty
      <material>yolks</material>. And with this dozen and a half of <material>chicken egg
      yolks</material> put one half ounce (others say sixty <material>eggs</material> and a half
    pound) of <material>female silk worm eggs</material>. And after carefully luting the flask (I do
    not know if air will be needed for the generation) and bury it in the heat of the
      <material>manure</material> up to the neck, and leave it there until several
      <animal>worms</animal> are engendered and then remove the flask and do not bury it in the
      <material>manure</material> anymore. But put it on the hot layer of the
      <material>manure</material> until all the <animal>worms</animal> are eaten and consume one
    another by shriveling and stirring, and only one remains. Once this has happened, you must lure
    it at regular intervals, day and night, with the assistance of two men, who will care for it in
    shifts, and you will lure it with an <material>egg yolk</material> covered in
      <material>gold</material> leaf or with a liquid <material>yolk</material> into which the
      <material>gold</material> leaf has been incorporated. And be careful that it does not miss
    such fodder (some say one <material>egg yolk</material> per hour, others say three, but the
    thing itself will demonstrate the practice). So nourished in this way it will grow in two month
    or seven weeks and will become like a <animal>serpent</animal>, one span and four fingers long,
    and one pound in weight, and as the wings will begin to develop, you must kill it, doing so with
    a <material>charcoal</material> fire in a ring around the bottle one span away from it, and at
    that time lute the bottle well so that it does not exhale.</block>

  <folio number="052v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f110.item"/>

  <block>or to be safer, go away until the fire is completely blown out and that everything is cold
    again. Because the exaltation may be dangerous. And for that moment, when you take it with some
    tongs, do cover your mouth with some good <material>vinegar</material> and have a protection and
    cover yourself with it. Once it has died out, put it into a cloth or a canvas made of
      <material>silk</material> and fold it and hold it to a board exposed to air and the sun will
    dry it. Once it is well dry, powder it in a mortar and keep this powder cautiously Because one
    ounce of this one thrown on 3 pounds of melted <material>♁</material> transforms it into a finer
      <material>☉</material> than the other one. But there is not so much pitch. You also have to
    choose the oldest <material>♁</material> possible which has often melted before and finely
    hammered into blades or other works, and at first purify it by melting and throwing it into some
      <material>honey</material> and <material>vinegar</material>. The completion time for such work
    is nine months from Saint John's day until the 25th April. </block>

</entry>
