<entry identifier="p056v_1">
    <folio number="056v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b9059316c/f118.item"/>
    <purpose type="advice"/>
    <activity type="painting"/>

    <heading>To paint</heading>

    <block>The <material>lacquer</material> and <material>rosette from Ghent</material> and
        elsewhere lose their color and die in contact with the air.</block>

    <block>Any <material>marble</material> on which a knife can [illegible] is not worth to grind
        fine colors.</block>

    <block>The <material>chalk</material> is not thick with <material>oil</material>, the
            <material>ceruse</material> is more appropriate but even better is the <material>white
            lead</material>. The <material>ceruse</material> is the whitest and is to grind firstly
        with some <material>water</material>, the white lead is grayish. But turns perfectly white
        with some <material>oil</material>.</block>

    <block>When you grind your colors, start by cleaning your workshop because if you raise some
        dust while walking that will damage your colors which will never be beautiful if they are
        not clean.</block>

    <block>The <material>Florey</material> must not be mingled with some <material>azur
            enamel</material> or anything else for it turns it into green.</block>

    <block><material>Ivory</material> is excellent to make a painter's' palette Knots of the fir tree The
        pear-tree and if it is walnut tree make sure to cut with the grain of the wood.</block>


    <block>You always have to stamp on <material>wood</material> to <material>oil paint</material>
        in order to fill holes and unevenness. And stamp with some [illegible] and
            <material>ceruse</material> mixed with oil, then soften with a feather which evens more
        than a brush. Or when the stamp is dry, rub it strongly off with a knife.</block>

    <block>To use some <material>azur enamel</material> with some <material>oil</material>, you have
        to choose the finest one and to make it thinner, do not grind for it turns white but wash it
        and because the bigger goes at the bottom, choose the one at the top of the
            <material>water</material> or pour the cloudy <material>water</material> out and pile
        the <material>azur</material>.</block>

    <folio number="057r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f119.image"/>
    <annotations>
        <annotation url="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/0B33U03wERu0eTGMwZG1nQk5KTFU" title="Gold Without Gold"/>
    </annotations>

    <block><material>Lake</material> takes a long time to dry in <material>oil</material> and for
        that reason you have to crush <material>glass</material> with it, but you have to choose
            <material>crystallin</material> because it is neater. And since it would be too
        difficult to be crushed by itself, you have to heat it red hot, then, when it is entirely
        red, throw it into cold <material>water</material> and it will crumble and pulverize itself
        to then be crushed easily. After being crushed with a lot of <material>water</material>, it
        looks like crushed <material>lead white</material>, but for this reason it has no body. I
        think it could be good for casting.</block>

    <block><material>Lead white</material> is made with <material>lead</material> sheets beaten
        gently and put under some manure.</block>

    <block>White <material>turpentine</material> varnish or <material>aspic oil</material> and
            <material>turpentine</material> is colored with powdered <material>turmeric</material>
        boiled together with it. It gives a <material>gold</material> color on
            <material>silver</material> which is even more beautiful when burnished. It dries within
        a quarter of an hour. <material>Aloes</material> would made an even brighter color but it
        takes time to dry whereas the other one dries within a quarter of an hour in winter as well
        as in summer.</block>

    <block> Good <material>lake</material> moistened with <material>saliva</material> quickly
        darkens. That from <place>Florence</place> is mixed with too much
        <material>gum</material>.</block>

    <block>If you apply one layer of <material>printers' ink</material> on
            <material>velvet</material> and apply <material>gold</material> leaves and then stretch
        it, it looks grainy as if it was powdered with <material>gold</material> sprinkled on
        it.</block>

    <block><material>Vermillion</material> crushed by itself is wan and pale but is more beautiful
        when it is crushed with <material>lake</material>.</block>

    <block>In order to remove the <material>grease</material> off <material>marbles</material>, one
        crushes <material>ordinary ashes</material> on it, which afterward are good to make the
        first primer coat of a painting to be done in <material>oil</material> in order to seal the
        cracks and veins of the <material>wood</material>. They are thicker than
            <material>chalk</material> and are quite greasy. They are mingled with the aforesaid
            <material>chalk</material> or with colors collected from the vessel that is used to
        clean brushes, and they are desiccative and spare the colors. Once this primer coat has been
        made on the <material>wood</material>, it is scrubbed with a knife until even. After, one
        makes a second coat with <material>ceruse</material> or with the poorest colors mixed
        together. On an <material>oil</material> canvas painting one only applies one coat and the
        mixed <material>ashes</material> can be used. Also, after crushing a color, one crushes the
            <material>interior of a large loaf of bread</material> in order to remove the
            <material>grease</material> off the <material>marble</material>.</block>
</entry>
