<entry identifier="p057v_2">
    <folio number="057v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f120.item"/>
    <purpose type="obeservation"/>
    <activity type="coloring"/>

    <heading>Painter</heading>

    <block>Good <material>crayons</material> are not made with <material>glue</material> but with
            <material>women's milk</material>.</block>

    <block>Images made of <material>card</material> have to be dipped in some very fine and
        clarified melted <material>rosin</material> once they have dried. This strengthens them or
        they will turn flaccid in wet weather.</block>

    <block><place>Venice</place> masks are made with a molding hollow and the face covered with
            <material>copper</material>.</block>

    <block>The Flemish do not use other white colors for <material>oil</material> painted skin
        colors after some <material>white lead</material> for the <material>ceruse</material> turns
        them yellow.</block>

    <block>The 4 or 5 years old and clear <material>nut oil</material> is the best anti-dust color.
        The one slowly squeezed from the press similar to <material>almond oil</material> is white
        even if the <material>nuts' skin</material> is peeled off.</block>

    <folio number="058r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f121.image"/>

    <block>You must make at least three layers of flesh color in order to paint faces in
            <material>oil</material>. And to begin, one places the black and shadow where it is
        appropriate. After, the highlighting with <material>lead white</material> must not be placed
        on the black. Flesh colors and [missing word] containing <material>ceruse</material> will
        yellow in five or six months, but <material>lead white</material> does not change.</block>

    <block><material><place>Florence</place> lake</material> is better than
            <material>lake</material> from <place>Flanders</place> because in
            <place>Florence</place> they make the best dyes. To make a beautiful flesh color, the
        reddest and brightest <material>lake</material> is the best, because those that are purple
        and violet as a result of the addition of too much <material>alum</material> look like the
        flesh of someone that is very cold. That is why women who want to color their cheeks crush
                <material><place>Florence</place> lake</material> very finely, then fill a little
            <material>cotton</material> with it, which they then wrap in a little fine
            <material>cambric</material>. And thus they rub the <material>lake</material> on their
        cheeks and then, with another clean <material>cotton</material>, they soften it.</block>

    <block><material>Crystallin</material> having been crushed in <material>water</material> appears
        to have body, but in <material>oil</material> it does not have any. It is crushed with
            <material>lake</material> and with <material>bitumen</material>, which would not dry for
        a very long time otherwise.</block>

    <block><material>Aspic oil</material> is commonly put with <material>lead white</material>, not
        entirely pure but mixed with a little <material>walnut oil</material>. The said
            <material>aspic oil</material> will not be good for <material>lake</material> and colors
        that do not have body because it will make them crack, but with those that have body and are
        somewhat greasy, it is quite appropriate.</block>

    <block><material>Verdigris</material> and <material>orpiment</material> must be first crushed
        with <material>urine</material> rather than thinned with <material>oil</material>. Thus they
        are beautiful and do not fade.</block>

</entry>
