<entry identifier="p058v_5">
    <folio number="058v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f122.item."/>
    <purpose type="observation"/>

    <heading>
        <tool>Brushes</tool>
    </heading>

    <block>When the color has dried inside them and you want to clean them soak them in some
            <material>spike lavender oil</material> and they will turn immediately soft again as
        before, then you will finish to clean them in some <material>nut oil</material>.
            <material>Nut oil</material>is not as appropriate to soften them as the <material>spike
            lavender</material> one which is clear like water and penetrates and is not as thick as
        the <material>nut oil</material>. Brush handles are made by those who work with care from
        porcupine hairs, by some others from fine branches of Turkish <material>wood</material> with
        which they also make small sticks to rest their hand when they are painting</block>

    <block position="left-bottom">To work properly on small scale you need some very fine brushes
        with a strong point. And because the <material>hair</material> taken from a
            <animal>squirrel</animal>'s tale is mollesin, the most careful ones use the of oldest
                <material><animal>rats</animal>' hair</material> and even of
            <animal>dormouses</animal> if they can find some and put two or three in the middle of a
        brush. These brushes draw a straight line like a quill and all the other hairs stick to
        them. The <material>hair of a <animal>stone marten</animal></material> or of a
            <animal>weasel</animal> and small animals used to make some <material>musk</material>
        are even better for just one <material>hair</material> is necessary in a brush</block>

    <folio number="059r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f123.item"/>

    <block><material>Lake and white lead</material> and <material>ceruse</material> are easy to work
        with some <material>oil</material>, but every kind of <material>azure</material> is
        difficult. And to make a beautiful <material>azure</material>, one has to lay it not with
        big strokes of the brush but with fine strokes of the end. Not only for <material>azurite
            ash</material> and <material>azur</material> from <place>Acre</place> but mainly for
            <material>enamel azur</material> which has to be very fine, otherwise you will not be able to work
        with it unless with hard work and you have to mingle it with some
            <material>turpentine</material> to thicken it and and to mingle it with some
            <material>white lead</material>. Any <material>azure</material> must not neither be
        ground nor washed for it loses its color and become pale. But put some of it powdered on
        your palette and you moisten it bit by bit with some <material>nut oil</material> or
            <material>turpentine</material>, dip a knife point in some <material>oil</material> and
        then mix it bit by bit on the said palette</block>

</entry>
