<entry identifier="p084v_a4">

<folio number="084v"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f174.image"/>


<activity type="sand making"/>

<heading><material>Sand</material>, for the most excellent <material>lead</material> of all, for large and small reliefs</heading>

<body>
<purpose type="making"/>
I took white <material>lead</material> and crushed it dry on <tool>porphyry</tool>, to make it very fine. Then I moistened it a lot with very well beaten <material>egg white</material>, so that it became like a paste, by making it stick together perfectly with the <tool>flat of a knife</tool>. I let it rest for a while.
</body>

<body position="left-bottom">
X
</body>

<body position="left-bottom">
<purpose type="advice"/>
Mix it well with the <tool>knife</tool>
</body>

<folio number="085r"
  url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f175.image"/>

  <body>
    <purpose type="making">
    and place it on a flat well-clean <tool>table</tool>, and since it has a desiccative quality, I knew it would dry out.  I left it to dry for a while to reduce it to a powder and mold it with sand, it having been ground into small pieces with my fingers and the sharp side of a <tool>knife</tool>.  I oiled my medal because <material>oil</material> cleans it without damaging it. And after cleaning and drying the medal with a <tool>cloth</tool> and small <tool>bristle brush of <material>pork skin</material></tool>, I lightly oiled it once more with clear <material>walnut oil</material>, and gently swiped it with a <tool>cloth</tool> so that [the medal] would not be too oiled; having already considered that in this way [the medal] should come out easily, because the <material>white lead</material>, wet with <material>glair</material>, which would not damage the oil. This worked very well.  I molded a medal very cleanly in high relief, without it having any lumps, which a lot of good sands such as felt, <material>burnt bone</material>, and <material>iron dross</material> failed to do on the first attempt. I re-cooked it and my mold became hard like marble. And then I knew that sands used to mold big relief must be very moist with some kind of water, which gives body and firmness, like <material>egg white</material>, <material>gummed water</material>, [or] one [water] boiled with <material>elm root</material>. And lightly oil your medal. It can take as many firings as you want because it is as hard as glass.  But <material>soft lead</material> and <material>sour tin</material> must be cast at a very hot temperature.
  </body>

  <body>
    <purpose type="advice">
    Since that moment, I have realized that even though this sand is excellent, can be cast often and molds very neatly, it is fat and it makes bubbles. In this way, the <material>soft lead</material> does not suit the mold well.  But I have tried to mix it with <material>lean sand</material>, such as <material>pumice</material>, <material>metal scrapings</material>, and similar things, in order to give it body, and to help it come off easily, because lean sand [alone] does not come off easily; and yet it takes metal well.
  </body>

  <body position="left-top">
    Try to mix <material>white lead</material> or <material>minium</material> with other sands.
  </body>

  <body position="left-top">
    X
  </body>

  <body position="left top">
    <purpose type="advice"/>
  Oil and smear with <material>aspic oil</material>, which will disappear when reheated, because the oil causes bubbling.
  </body>

  <body position="left-middle">
    <purpose type="advice"/>
    It is necessary to mold with <material>egg white</material>, and then mix it well. And once it is in the <tool>box mold</tool>, beat it well on the top with a <tool>pestle</tool>, or something else clean. This helps to make molding better and come out more easily.
  </body>

  <body position="left-middle">
    <purpose type="advice"/>
    It is best to fill the <tool>box mold</tool> in one go, because the mixture made of several sands, and the one from mines, that you use to fill the <tool>box mold</tool>, damages it.
  </body>


</entry>
