<entry identifier="p087v_a3">

  <folio number="087v"
    url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f180.image"/>

    <activity type="sandmold making"/>

    <heading><material>Sand</material> from sand pit from <place>Toulouse</place></heading>

    <block>
      <purpose type="making"/>
      In order to use <material>sand</material> from a sandpit for casting, filter it through a <tool>double sieve</tool>, then having mixed it with <material>molten resin</material> it burns and heats, and becomes all red and hot as iron. Once it has cooled down it is completely black and can be pulverised on <tool>porphyry</tool> very well. Having prepared it like this and checked the smoothness of the surface with my nail, I moistened it with <material>egg white</material> and beat it vigorously, until it was not a paste anymore but a powder. I found this sand to release the cast very well, and molded very clean in lead and tin with it, however it needs to be reheated and at leisure.
    </block>

    <block>
      <purpose type="making"/>
      Others beat it strongly in a <tool>mortar</tool>, in small amounts at a time, thus it detaches and comes out very fine; then they bake it moderately, just enough to dry it, and then they crush it dry on <tool>porphyry</tool>. Thus it is made almost impalpable, and yet not too dry , and it retains the consistency and the binding quality of the earth to which it is related, and is better than when it is burnt. When you moisten it with <material>egg white</material> and pass it through a <tool>sponge</tool> it releases  very clean for a low relief, but not a figure in high relief. Considering this, since then I experimented  with moistening it only with strong <material>vinegar</material>. That way it releases a figure I previously had not been able to release from the mold. I think that even when you wet the finest sort with <material>egg white</material>, or in a similar fashion, or the thick sort to fill  chasses with <material>water</material>, <material>salt</material>, or <material>vinegar</material>, they do not mix so well. However, given that they are of one and the same nature, and are similarly moistened, they espouse each other, and hold together.
    </block>

    <block>
      <purpose type="advice"/>
      To mold well, when your <material>sands</material> are prepared, mold in one day. Bake slowly the next day, then cast the other.
    </block>

    <block position="left-middle">
      <purpose type="advice"/>
      It is necessary to choose <material>sand</material> that like comes in clods and lumps, and deep down in the earth, because commonly the one near the surface is too much akin to earth, whereas the deep one is similar to rock.
    </block>

    <block position="left-middle">
      <purpose type="advice"/>
      I have sometimes molded with pure <material>lead</material> cast very clean hot, and the example as well as the principal were very clean, but since the <material>vinegar</material> gives it little binding, it held only for one cast.
    </block>

</entry>
