<entry identifier="p107r_a2">
<folio number="107r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f219.image"/>
<purpose type="making"/>
<activity type="casting"/>

<heading>[Information on casting]</heading>

<block>The <material>sand</material> mixture is made of two thirds of ground <material>plaster</material>, reheated as it is said before, and of one part of <material>reddened tiles</material> which are finely ground afterwards. Use also <material>stone alum</material>, half of the quantity of the <material>tiles</material>. Use two full <unit>pots</unit> of <material>plaster</material>, one <unit>pot</unit> of tile and half a <unit>pot</unit> of <material>stone alum</material>. Do not use too much <material>stone alum</material> because that binds the <material>sand</material>, and allow <material>sand</material> to withstand fire without cracking or breaking. Without it <material>[stone alum]</material> sand would not withstand fire, you can use it for all kind of <material>metal</material>, but for <material>gold</material> add a bigger quantity of <material>stone alum</material>, add also <material>crocum ferri</material>, because they [these filings] attract <material>gold</material>.</block>

<block>All the <material>sands</material> you will cast, must withstand fire very well, it must withstand high temperature without spoiling anything.</block>

<block>It is difficult to grind <material>stone alum</material>, and it cannot be sieved, you must grind it on a <tool>marble slab</tool>. The <material>white [stone alum] powder</material> the apothecaries sell is good, it is easy to crush it into a <tool>mortar</tool>, use the <tool>pestle</tool> slowly, that way you will make it [the stone alum] very fine.</block>

<block><material>Crocum ferri</material> must be heated into a <tool><profession>glassworker</profession>'s furnace</tool> during four <time>days</time>.</block>
<folio number="107v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f220.image"/>

<block>Molds for fine things, like <plant>wormwood</plant> or something similar, can only be used once, dip the molds into <material>water</material> before breaking them. Things twice reheated are dissolve easily into <material>water</material>. If you don't do that your work will be hard to be stripped of the mold without being spoiled.</block>

<block>Good <material>stone alum</material> is white and as shiny as white silk, this <material>stone alum</material> is made of long pieces, as long as a finger, and is very fragile and woolly and fluffy. <material>Stone alum</material> made of <material>stone</material> is harder and not so good. The best quality can be found in <place>France</place> near <place>Ronan</place>. For our <material>sand</material>, stone alum must be crushed into a <tool>mortar</tool>, and must be ground on the marble again. Don't even think about sieving it because this <material>matter</material> is fat and woolly, it wouldn't pass through any <tool>sieve</tool> because of the very fine and soft filaments. These filaments give the <material>sand</material> a much greater binding effect than <material>natural wool</material> or even the <material>filler the foundry owner uses</material> for big works, because <material>natural wool</material> and filler burn and <material>stone feather alum</material> resists fire.</block>

<block>When you cast surround the <material>sand</material> of your mold with very beaten <material>greasy earth</material>. Make a circle around your mold with this <material>earth</material>.</block>

<block><foreign language="Latin">Archanum omnibus fere reconditum est in re fusoria,

v{idelicet} res exprimenda formis, sive herba sit sive animal

ut lucerta, inmergatur primum in vini spiritum

aprime rectificatum, deinde pulvere composito aspergatur

sive illinatur (si pulvis in formam pultis redactus sit, ut

assolet)</foreign></block>

<block>When you want to mold something hollow, the core must be made of the same matter, if the <animal>snake</animal> or the animal is curved or folded you must do your core in several pieces.</block>

<block>Try [to see] if <material>distilled vinegar</material> is good for eating away, it will dissolve the animal inside the hollow mold.</block>

<block position="left-top">If you know that your <material>plaster</material> cannot endure fire without breaking, do not take the recipe of the mixture literally, sometimes you can add less <material>stone alum</material> than above. Because <material>stone alum</material> soften molds. Once reheated do not grind the <material>stone alum</material> again, leave it ground as the apothecaries did. It will not prevent the cast from being neat, and will give more binder to your cast. When the mold holds the color of the brick and is reddened then it will be harder.</block>

<folio number="108r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f221.image"/>

<block>To hold the cores, some [people] use <tool>wire</tool> made of the same metal as that to be cast because it boils down and is made similarly, but when it is melted or pliant the core varies. Other [people] find it serves them better to use sharpened <tool><material>iron</material> wire</tool> about the borders because it holds more firmly, and having fine points it does not rise up any more than the point of a <tool>needle</tool> and one can apply <material>gold</material> or <material>silver</material> on this rather than putting it in works [where] one makes a hole in the work with a small <tool>chisel</tool>.</block>

<block><material>Spirits</material> prevent the <material>sand</material> from bubbling and do not make little holes on the borders of the mold if the thing to be molded is very damp, the holes and farts and bubbling does not make it in the place of the mold which is thick but at the borders which are more delicate.</block>

<block>One casts ordinary <material>silver</material> of the sort goldsmiths coarsely work, which is made with <material>mediocre alloys</material>. And when one casts with <material>solder</material>, it runs even better.</block>

<block><material>Spalt</material> is a whitish stone which can be found in <place>Germany</place>, mainly in <place>Augsburg</place> from which can be made the most excellent sand that can be found for [casting] <material>lead</material>, <material>tin</material>, <material>copper</material>, <material>silver</material> and <material>gold</material>. And the more it is used, the better it is. It is clean for casting flat things in a frame. For rounded things, it is not as attractive [because it] does not hold in the fire as the aforementioned [things] composed of <material>plaster</material>.</block>

<block>The snippings of [a] large [piece of] <material>greasy leather</material> are good to cast in melted <material>copper</material> and <material>brass</material> because they clean it and take away from it all its filth.</block>
</entry>
