<entry identifier="p109r_5">
<folio number="109r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f223.image"/>
<purpose type="making"/>
<purpose type="observation"/>

<heading>Molding <animal>snakes</animal></heading>

<block><activity type="casting"/><activity type="keeping animals"/>When you get them for molding, if it is possible, do not remove their teeth if you [think you might] want to keep them, because having had their teeth removed, it hurts their gums and mouths, and they can no longer eat.  You can keep [the snakes] in a <tool>barrel</tool> full of <material>bran</material> or even better of <material>earth</material>, in a cool place, or in a <material>glass</material> <tool>bottle</tool>.  And give them some live <animal>frog</animal> or other live <animal>animal</animal> because they do not eat anything that is dead. Also I have noticed that<folio number="109v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f224.image"/> when they want to bite or to eat something, they [snakes] do not go at it head on, but sideways and by sinuous coiling, as do <name type="personal">Satan</name> and his henchmen. The <animal>snake</animal> has a small head, but a very large body; the entryway to sin seems small and inconsequential, but the consequences are great indeed. A <animal>snake</animal> can abstain from eating for seven or eight days, once he has swallowed a <animal>frog</animal>, and can swallow three or four <animal>frogs</animal>, one after the other, and what it has devoured does not rot and is not digested all at once in its stomach, but each part little by little, i.e. the bones and everything. The rest is just as fresh as when the <animal>snake</animal> ate it, such that when one bothers and torments it, it spits out what it swallowed up, which, in part, is totally digested, with the other part as fresh as if the <animal>frog</animal> were alive. It can hold a swallowed <animal>frog</animal> down for two or three <time>hours</time> and spit it out alive.</block>
</entry>
