<entry identifier="p112r_4">
<folio number="112r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f229.image"/>
<purpose type="making"/>
<activity type="keeping animals"/>

<heading>Killing the <animal>animal</animal> to mold</heading>

<block>You must have been careful not to hurt it while capturing it. If you have a stock [of animals] and you wish to keep them for a long time, place it in a <tool>glass bottle</tool> with <material>bran</material> or in a large <tool>barrel</tool> half full of damp fresh <material>earth</material>. Give them <animal>frogs</animal> to eat, live rather than dead, because should you keep them without feeding them, they would wither and become emaciated, and their skin would become saggy and wrinkled. Therefore, the sooner after its capture you mold it, the better it will come out. And kill it in the following manner: place it in a clean <tool>bottle</tool> or <tool>vessel</tool> so that [the animal] does not carry any dust; fill [the bottle] with enough good <material>vinegar</material> and <material>urine</material> so as to cover [the animal]. Shake [the bottle] and torment [the animal] inside there until it is dead which should take an hour or half an hour. But if you are in a hurry</block>

<block position="left-bottom"> To know if [the animal] is quite dead, take it out of the vinegar and take it by the tail. If it moves its tail, do not mold it because it still has feelings, and when pricking [its members], it would remove itself and harm the mold.</block>

<block position="left-bottom">Water snakes do not bite much.</block>

<folio number="112v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f230.image"/>

<block>to cast, force feed it your <animal>animal</animal> some good <material>spirits</material> or mix a bit of <material>spirits</material> with the <material>vinegar</material>. And soon it will be dead without any wounds that would deform it. As for large <animal>animals</animal>, for which it is necessary to have a lot of <material>spirits</material>, one uses <material>vinegar</material> and <material>urine</material>, but for small ones, spirits only are needed, and it will be done quicker.</block>

<block>When your <animal>animal</animal> is dead, take it out and clean it very carefully, relieving it of its old skin if it sheds, of its parasites like <animal>lizards</animal> have, and then apply it.</block>

<block position="left-top"> in a glass, and submerge, continuously holding the head of the animal. Or if it is not very big, put the whole thing in.</block>

<block position="left-top"> Be advised that before it dies, you must open it eyes, by blocking its eyelids with a bit of wax or something else.</block>
</entry>
