<entry identifier="p113r_1">
<folio number="113r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f231.image"/>
<purpose type="making"/>
<activity type="casting"/>

<heading>Wetting sand and molding the first cast</heading>

<block>Have a <tool>porringer</tool> of <material>leaded earth</material> of such a size that it can hold the wet <material>sand</material> which will be needed to fill your mold in one go, which is better than in two gos, because if you do not throw the second load of <material>sand</material> in very quickly, there is a risk that while you are preparing it, the first one will take and become solid,</block>

<folio number="113v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f232.image"/>

<block>and this way, while heating it again, the two casts will dissolve. Therefore, have several dishes of various sizes with a pouring beak in order to cast better. In these, pour some regular fountain <material>water</material> and mix into it <unit>as much as an egg # can hold</unit> of <material>sal ammoniac water</material>, mixed as described. If you want to cast <material>lead</material> or <material>tin</material> - because one would need more for casting <material>gold</material> or <material>silver</material> - having the water in your dish, add the <material>sand</material> and not the other way around [by adding the water to the sand], and adjust it with such attentiveness that, while mixing it vigorously and wetting it quickly with a <tool>wooden spoon</tool>, it does not become thicker than <material>mustard</material>.  And in such a way cast [i.e., pour] first the clearest part, as is always at the surface, by shaking it a little higher in your mold.  And doing so, since your <animal>animal</animal> is nearly covered, Once your animal is covered, blow on it very strongly to eliminate the small bubbles from your soaked <material>sand</material>. Then pour immediately the rest which is at the bottom and which is thicker than the upper part, fill your mold to the thickness mark you have made.<figure identifier="fig_p113v_4" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5bEE5QmFaQWxUYm8" position="middle-middle"/> And while casting do not forget to shake your mold, that way your soaked sand runs and get in through every parts. Also tip your mold up on the side of the head, which is higher than the body. That way the contents of your mold will have the same thickness, and you'll spare <material>sand</material>. This being done with care, your sand will harden within a quarter of an <time>hour</time>. Then peel the clay contour which can be used later. Let it dry a little bit, than separate your mold from the slab of earth, and you can mold properly straight after. Cut away the extra parts with a knife, and make it mandore shaped. You can reuse the clay frame. Scrape away what's on the back of the mold, because this part is the weakest; do not forget to make notches around it, that way the second cast would bind much better<figure identifier="fig_p113v_5" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5V29QdUxZVmxCUDQ" position="middle-bottom"/> and would not move.</block>

<block position="left-top">Your half mold, in one shot and one mix is the best.</block>

<block position="left-top">#
or two eggs, because there is no danger if there is more. If you cast twice, just add <material>sal ammoniac water</material> into the first pouring.</block>

<block position="left-top">Make your mixture as clear as a <material>pureed broth</material>, or <material>starch water</material>, the one women use make their <material>starch</material>. It is not a problem if the mixture is very thin because <material>sand</material> settles in the bottom and water stays on top of it, which we scape as too weak and soft. It will not take long to harden, because burned things dry rapidly.</block>

<block position="left-bottom"><figure identifier="fig_p113v_3" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dEdzS040X3RjbkU"/>If you don't fill your mold with soaked <material>sand</material> at one go, do mix your second cast with the top part of the first cast, stir with a <tool>spoon</tool>, or the stick you had took to soak your <material>sand</material>.</block>

<block position="left-bottom">You do not need to add <material>sal ammoniac water</material> if you cast small molds which do not need to be reheated too long. However it is better to add some.</block>
</entry>
