<entry identifier="p114r_1">
<folio number="114r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f233.image"/>

<annotations>
        <annotation url="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/0BwJi-u8sfkVDLU9qZ0xaSUxRU00" title="Bread as Mediating Material: Tactile Memory and Touch in Ms. Fr. 640, fols. 29r, 114v, 129v, 130r (Le Pouésard)"/>
    </annotations>
<purpose type="making"/>

<heading>Second Casting</heading>

    <block><activity type="casting"/>When you have well molded the first part of the <animal>animal</animal>, that is to say the back, the spine, and the entire top part, and when the half-mold where the part is encased is hard enough <figure identifier="fig_114r_2" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5SWVndzB0aEk5MWs" position="left-top"/> turn over the bottom and the sides of the belly, sometimes using a <tool>knife</tool> for the thicker parts, and then with a <tool>pen-knife</tool> for the places where the more fragile parts are encased, like legs, tail, and similar things. Because the head is higher, you will have to dig deeper to expose it and do a deeper notch that has to be well exposed, by enlarging it from the outside, in order for the second mold that you cast on top of it releases well. A process for which the <animal>animal</animal> himself can be useful because his nature so permits. However, make sure that you reveal the <animal>lizard's</animal> throat more than you would do a <animal>snake</animal>, because the <animal>lizard</animal> has big jaws and big bones that do not cast as easily, and has deep ears in which the <material>wet sand</material> is not as easy to remove. But you will avoid all of this if you expose half of the head and those things that you know do not release easily. When everything is well exposed, blow over it and wipe each part again with a <tool>cloth made of swine hair</tool>, slightly dampened into <material>salt water</material> or <material>clear water</material>, do that gently, that way the lower part of your uncovered <animal>animal</animal> will be very neat. # <material>🝋</material> Once it is done, dip the covered side of your mold into <material>water</material> for a <foreign language="Latin">pater noster</foreign>. It will suck <material>water</material> inside, that way when you'll rub with <material>oil</material> the uncovered side, the <material>oil</material> will remain on the top, and to prevent the second cast which you will cast on top from sticking. Dip your mold into <material>water</material>, take a particularly <tool>fine brush</tool> and rub with <material>oil</material> the entire mold but the <animal>animal</animal>; it should not be touched with <material>oil</material>. Make sure to use you brush between the parts and on all the fragile parts. And if by mistake <material>oil</material> is soaked, dip the mold into <material>water</material>, as it is said above, and drop by drop the <material>oil</material> will come back to the top.</block>

<block position="left-top">Mold small <animal>animals</animal> as big ones, however, for small animals, use very <tool>fine tacks</tool> made of <material>cords of cittern</material>, short and long ones.</block>

<figure identifier="fig_p114r_1" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NVR5Y2FtZHM0ck0" position="left-top"/>

<block position="left-top">remove all the little <tool>tacks</tool> with the help of very small flat <tool>pincers</tool>. # then + [illegible] # However, leave the <tool>tack</tool> which is pinned into the throat so that it will help you to turn the head over, because it is sunk deeper than any other part, because when you drew the plan, you put higher up. It is at the level of the head that you must make the biggest notch and you should start at that notch to expose and then keep following by looking at the traces left by the <tool>tacks</tool>.</block>

<block position="left-bottom"># and if a small piece of nail, or piece of tail, or other fine things separate from the mold, put a little piece of <material>wax</material> between them, and join them with the tip of a hot <tool><material>iron</material> wire</tool>, then smooth it in your mold with a <tool>knife</tool>, and make notches on the sides in order for the other half of the mold to adhere to it. <material>🝋</material> </block>

<figure identifier="fig_p114r_6" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5TTRuWU8yVktnc3M" position="left-bottom"/>

<folio number="114v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f234.image"/>

<block>This thus prepared, put your first half-mold on the disc of <material>clay</material>, surround it with a <material>clay</material> circle and do a thickness mark similar to the first one. Then, with a rather <tool>thick brush</tool>, wet with <material>spirits</material> all your <animal>animal's</animal> exposed half, without, if possible, missing any part, because therein lies the secret to casting neatly. Then, as fast as possible before the <material>spirits</material> evaporate, soak your <material>sand</material>, and cast it, shaking, blowing, and moving the mold, as you did for the first one, making sure that what you pour first on the <animal>animal</animal> is clearer than the rest, so that it is soaked everywhere and highlights the finer parts. So, leave it for fifteen <unit>minutes</unit> so it sets, then remove the <material>clay</material> circle and disc. And, with a <tool>knife</tool>, join you two molds together in a longish form, like a mandore, as we say, because of how you cast. Then soak a little in <material>water</material> the whole mold up to the level of the joints. Because this is another secret to separate them more easily. Otherwise, you would break everything. Separate them like this skillfully. After this, gently and patiently remove half of the <animal>animal</animal> still in the mold, pulling it sometimes on one side and sometimes on the other, in order to avoid breaking it, or ruining parts of the mold. The mold, being empty, rejoin both half so that no <material>dust</material> comes in, and put them aside until you want to heat them up, make the <tool>runners</tool>, the <tool>vents</tool> and put the <tool>clamps</tool>. As for the <animal>animal</animal>, to avoid it drying, and in order to be be able to use it to mold 4 or 5 of times, put it on <material>water</material>. I believe that it would be better preserved in <material>spirits</material>. However, it would be best to make the 4 or 5 molds the same day because these <animal>animals</animal> rot and will smell within the <unit>day</unit>. Having left your molds to dry out, for they will stay humid for at least a <unit>month</unit>, make the vents for one half.</block>

<figure identifier="fig_p114v_1" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dmlRQm1lTjc4aXc" position="left-top"/>

<block position="left-top">+ Note that once you have made your second casting, if you left your mold without opening it for a <unit>day</unit> or a <unit>night</unit>, you would then need to put it into hot <material>water</material> or reheat it, rather than open it, like for the <animal>crab</animal>.</block>

<block position="left-top">If after both halfs of the <foreign language="French">noyau</foreign> have set and hardened, it would not open if you did not dip it into <material>water</material>. But as you dip the back of your mold into <material>water</material>, <material>oil</material> comes back to the top and touches the joints which separates them.</block>

<block position="left-middle">However, be sure that your second mold is thick enough, and hard enough otherwise it could break while dipping it into <material>water</material> if you want to open it. To avoid this mistake dip the entire mold into <material>water</material> and rub it everywhere, if the mold has set enough it will harden. Then take both molds with a <tool>rough cloth</tool>, in order to grip it better. Then strongly separate the molds as if you wanted to tear <material>bread</material> apart.  But in case it breaks, rejoin them, and fortifies the joints with <tool>clamps</tool>.</block>

<figure identifier="fig_p114v_4" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5NmZxVUxKTmhYSXM" position="middle-bottom"/>

<figure identifier="fig_p114v_3" url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5dkk3MW10YzNIbDg" position="right-bottom"/>

<block position="right-bottom">Afterwards you can repair the mistakes with a small pair of <tool>scissors</tool>.</block>

</entry>
