<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p131r_5">
    <folio number="131r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f267.item.r="/>
    <heading>Molded wax</heading>
    <block>
        <material>Wax</material> representations made from <material>white lead</material> and
            <material>cerussite</material> are not made to be burned and melted in a mold where you
        want to cast <material>silver</material> and <material>gold</material>; this would make it
        brittle. Moreover if you use such a mold, the <material>wax</material> would be stripped
        thanks to the violence of the fire which makes it boil, and the mixture made of
            <material>cerrusite</material> or any other metal would attack the mold. That's why if
        you want to sketch things </block>
    <block position="left-bottom"> +White <material>wax</material> is more delicate than the other,
        and it doesn't leave any filth when you want to mold it as a core, or to mold hollow. </block>
    <folio number="131v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f268.item.r=
        "/>
    <block> to be cast with <material>gold</material> and <material>silver</material>. Do not add to
        your wax all the drugs you are preparing, but only melted <material>sulphur</material>, as
        the candle melts, and also candle smoke. Melted <material>sulphur</material> falls down to
        the bottom of your mold, but lets the wax keeps some of its quality, melting it but leaving
        it a little firm. You can thus melt your wax representation on fire. If your
            <material>wax</material> is composed of <material>cerussite</material> or something
        similar, you need to put your mold into boiling water. </block>
    <!--margin block on the next page -->
    <block position="left-top"> You don't need all this to mold flat representations made of wax,
        because the <material>wax</material> can be removed completely from the mold, and won't
        remain inside it. </block>
</entry>
