<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p132v_2">
    <folio number="132v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f270.item.r="/>

    <heading>Crocum ferry</heading>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <activity type="making sand"/>
    <block> After I processed it with <material>vinegar</material> and reddened under heat, I had it
        ground very finely on the <material>porphyry</material>, until there could be no ruggedness
        felt under the nails. Then I soaked it in very good <material>vinegar</material> for 2 or 3
        days, stirring the mixture several times a day. Then I boiled it and made it red-hot in a
            <tool>pot</tool>, and put the whole thing into an air furnace. I obtained a mass full of
        eyes, but that crumbled finely between the fingers. I mixed half as much as <material>stone
            alum</material> in the sand. I diluted the sand very thinly, and molded a very small
            <animal>lizard</animal>, which molded very cleanly and finely. <material>Crocum
            ferry</material> does not make the mold harder, but makes it firmer. When your mold is
        soft and fat under your nail, it means that the <material>crocum</material> is good, very
        fine and well prepared. You can add any quantity of crocum, your mold will not be damaged
        because it is a friend of <material>gold</material>. I think it would be the same with
            <material>silver</material>. And in order that molds made with it do not crack, make it
        with <material>needle filings</material>. </block>

    <block position="left-top"><material>Sand</material> is better made with distilled
            <material>vinegar</material>. </block>
    <block position="left-middle">You can add this <material>sand</material> to the molds you want
        to use to cast <material>silver</material>, because it make molds firmer, and when you
        scratch it, you will find it a bit rougher than the other molds not made from this
            <material>sand</material>. You mold very clean with this
        <material>sand</material>.</block>
    <block position="left-bottom">You can use this one for all molds, because it prevents them from
        cracking and bursting when heated. This <material>sand</material> withstands several casts
        for molding flat medals. <material>Sand</material> from <material>steel</material> or
            <material>needle filings</material> is redder and better. </block>
</entry>
