<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p132r_2">
    <folio number="132r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f269.item.r="/>
    <heading>How to anneal the molds</heading>
    <block> Light your charcoals from the forge, then place them in a line in a corner of the forge
        according to the size of your mold, in order that it be surrounded with 3 or 4 fingers of
        charcoals, particularly at the bottom of the mole, where it is thicker. Then put your molds
        on these charcoals -- and not on a grate as some people do -- because they would get too
        strong a heat. Let your furnace heat up gradually for a while, always adding burning
        charcoal. As long as the mold is humid, your charcoal will be dampened at the bottom, but
        when it is dry, the charcoals start to blaze. When one side of the mold is dry, turn over;
        when both sides are dry and don't smoke anymore, increase the heat and cover your mold with
        burning coals. When the mold starts being red, do not blow on it with small bellows, because
        the mold would burst. Similarly, when your mold becomes red-hot, keep it well covered with
        burning charcoals and do not uncover it because it would crack. Prevent the draft from a
        window from reaching it. Then let it cool down. </block>
    <block position="left-middle">When you want to anneal your molds, luted or not, do mark the
        belly of your mold, in order to place that side at the bottom, against the burning
        charcoals, because if the intensity of the heat made the mold crack, it would be better that
        it do so on the bottom part instead of the top part. </block>

    <block position="left-bottom"> If your mold is small, do not heat it as long, otherwise it would
        crack and be damaged. </block>
    <folio number="132v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f270.item.r="/>
    <block> dry by itself. When your mold starts to redden, it will soon be become completely
        red-hot. But make sure that its bottom is red-hot too, without any black spot. </block>

</entry>
