<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p133v_3">
    <folio number="133v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f272.image"/>
    <heading>Various animals entwined</heading>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <activity type="lifecasting"/>
    <block> You can entwine a <animal>snake</animal> with a <animal>lizard</animal>, each one biting the other, or a <animal>snake</animal> eating a
        <animal>frog</animal>, or a <animal>wall lizard</animal> or something similar. But since these interlacings cannot be
        stripped, cut what's possible, and allow the rest to burn. To make the mouth of the <animal>snake</animal>,
        which must stand high, hold a <animal>wall lizard</animal>, which is small and would need to be held in the
        air, because the snake's head is higher, put under the wall <animal>lizard</animal> a mound of earth suitable
        to support it. And if you place the mold in a furnace, the animal drying quickly, it will
        quickly shrink, then it will burn more easily. These interlacings are also made to mask
        wounds or defects on the animal which happen when we catch them. Do not forget to join with
        <material>wax</material>, applied carefully with a hot <tool>iron wire</tool>, all the parts of the animal which are one on
        top of the other, or those which are not well pressed on the slab of <material>clay</material>, so that the
        soaked <material>sand</material> does not remove them. Do that in order to </block>
    <folio number="134r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f273.image"/>
    <block> avoid putting <tool>pins</tool> that should not be put, only on the top of the head, the thickest
        parts of the body, and on the delicate parts like the middle of the lizard's feet, the nails
        of which you will drive into the <material>clay</material>, thus they won't move. Once your first mold is casted,
        peel away the belly of the animal, but do not forget to put some tenuous little pieces of
        <material>wax</material> at the tip of the lizard's feet. But if it is from a <animal>wall lizard</animal>, lightly cover all the
        sole of its feet with wax, which will be removed with the second cast. A cavity is left
        which will be fill these little fingers with metal. then rework it. Make sure that <material>wax</material> is
        fixed well on the parts of the animal which are one on top of the other, so that the soaked
        <material>sand</material> which comes in does not make them move. If that happened your jacket of <material>clay</material> would be
        spoiled and your mold wouldn't get the right thickness, would have holes, and would be
        spoiled. To obviate that you can make a thicker mold. If this occurs you could rework it in
        this fashion.</block>
</entry>
