<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p135v_a1">
    <folio number="135v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f276.item.r="/>"
    <heading>Casting <material>gold</material></heading>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <activity type="casting"/>
    <block> Take a <tool>crusol</tool> that can contain a certain amount, as you wish to place roughly crushed
        <material>borax</material> into it. Place [the borax] at the bottom and then the <material>gold</material> on top of it. Arrange the
        <material>coal</material> in the forge in such a way that the wind of the bellow will blow above the <tool>crusol</tool> and
        no on its side as it would cool it down and would not heat it enough. Also, make sure it is
        three good fingers away from the wall of the forge so that it is quite surrounded by coal.
        Allow the <tool>crusol</tool> to anneal until it is quite red. Then, have your boy strongly blow the
        bellow with long pushes, as in this manner it heats it better. Meanwhile, once the <material>gold</material> will
        be melted, blow a small bellow above it. Because [otherwise] the <material>gold</material> would turn sour and
        would acquire some kind of coat. As long as there will be some swirling smoke as you blow
        this way, it means that it is not soft enough for the cast. Therefore, uncover the melting
        pot and without displacing it and without stopping the bellow, tilt it towards you so you
        may well see what is inside. Throw a ferue of <material>borax</material> in it and blow wind towards it with the
        small bellow in a jerky fashion. Should there be <material>coal</material> inside, blow a bit stronger to make
        them come out. And if the <material>gold</material> still smokes and swirls, add <material>borax</material> again and blow above it.
        Beware that it is still sour and not soft enough, it will show a coat when you blow it as if
        it had cooled down. By contrast, if it does not show this sign, it is soft enough. Then,
        blow strongly so that it [the gold] is quite heated and once you think it is hot enough,
        throw colour on top of it in the <tool>crusol</tool> and the colour should be composed as following:
        <material>verdigris</material>, <material>saltpeter</material>, <material>sal ammoniac</material>, and a bit of borax. And continue blowing with the small
        bellows, and the <material>gold</material> will turn shiny like </block>
    <block position="left-top">If you cast in <material>gold</material> some piece of important [dimensions], lute your
        mold with the same <material>sand</material> or put <material>crocum</material> on it. </block>
    <block position="left-top">If you wish to cast some large work, or of important [dimensions],
        create at the bottom or at an extremity of the forge a vented furnace where you may hold
        your mold in the <material>sand</material> so red. </block>
    <block position="left-middle">One may cast two or three <unit>pounds</unit> of <material>gold</material>. </block>
<folio number="136r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f277.item.r="/>
    <block> a mirror. And once you will want to [start] casting, put a bit more colour in
        and let it rest a little, still blowing wind with both the small and the large bellows.
        Finally, place your mold quite red between the small molds or in a <tool>crusol</tool> full of <material>sand</material> quite
        hot and [start] casting. And once it will have stuck, you may, if you wish, throw it into
        water as <material>gold</material> does not get damaged like tin which breaks. </block>
    <block> To melt <material>gold</material> bullion, there is no need to blow above [the crusol] with the small bellow. </block>
    <block> For large works, the <tool>crusol</tool> made of <material>sand</material> has to be placed in a wind oven so that it is
        all red at the end of the furnace. </block>
    <block> <material>Gold</material>, when exposed to wind or when forged becomes black. But a bit of <material>aqua forte</material> removes
        [the black] instantly. </block>
    <block> If you have to forge a work made of <material>gold</material> on <material>brass</material>, as is done on small statues, put a
        <material>lead</material> sheet between the <material>gold</material> and the <material>brass</material>, and rather than anneal it and put it back in the
        fire, dip it in the <material>aqua forte</material> and it will be soft. </block>
    <block> It is enough for the cast to be of the same thickness as the medal, that it from the
        middle of the cast, up to the medal. But if the medal is very thick, one should not thicken
        the cast as a result, because a thick cast never comes out well. It may be done large to
        embrace the medal as much as possible. </block>
</entry>
