<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<entry identifier="p136v_1">
    <folio number="136v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f278.image"/>
    <heading><material>latten</material> casting </heading>
    <block> Take <material>latten</material> from <tool>skillet pans</tool>, used to make baby's
        cereal, which is doulx and apt for the cast. Some people say that <tool>counter</tool> from
            <place>Germany</place> contain a lot of <material>calamine</material>. However, when
        they are tempered, <material>calamine</material> evaporates, <material>calamine</material>
        mixed with melted <material>latten</material> always evaporates, because
            <material>latten</material> becomes red again, thanks to the reiteration of melting.
        However, fresh <material>calamine</material> and only fresh <material>calamine</material>,
        which is blended with remelted <material>latten</material>, makes
            <material>latten</material> run, and allow a clean cast. Because
            <material>calamine</material> which is added to remelted <material>latten</material> is
        half-damaged compared with its natural state. This half-damaged
            <material>calamine</material> make <material>latten</material> porous and agitated
        because it has a tendency to evaporate. Thus add only very fresh
            <material>calamine</material> to melted <material>latten</material>. Make sure to cast
        your mold very hot, you mold must become red-hot, like molds to cast
            <material>gold</material>, <material>silver</material>, <material>copper</material> and
        metal. If you pour fresh <material>calamine</material>, avoid its smoke which is pernicious.
        To cast a medal, I took thirty <material>counters</material> from <place>Germany</place> and
        xii <material>clous de rosette</material> made of <material>doulx latton</material>, like
        for claires medals which are made of soft <material>latten</material>. This matter contains
        a lot of <material>calamine</material> like all kind of yellow <material>latten</material>,
        and make a lot of smoke which prevent <material>latten</material> from running, and make it
        porous, that is why it is necessary to make many vents and to cast very hot, latten must be
        as white as water, or as melted <material>silver</material> or as a polished mirror of
        steel. The second fusion will come out much better because evaporated
            <material>calamine</material> does not make as much smoke. If you use a molding frame
        that does not break and holds its own, the second [casting] will come more neatly out of the
        mold, because the frame is impregnated with the smoke of <material>calamine</material>. If
        you add <materail>sal ammoniac</materail> to your <material>latten</material>, this latten
        will be clear and shiny, but will be even more shiny with <material>huile
            tingente</material>. Do not use another <material>sand</material> than the above
        mentioned to mold a <material>noyau</material>, and the mold must become red-hot, like a
        mold to cast <material>gold</material>. Make a lot of vents. If you cast yellow
            <material>latten</material> with the prepared tutty you will not get any smoke. </block>


    <block position="left-top"> This metal is capricious to cast because of the smoke of the
        calamine. Do not leave it out of the fire, as some do with silver. Because when air or wind
        touch it, the mold gets cold at once. When you cast it, this metal always leaves burrs, like
        when casting glass. <profession>Foundry workers</profession> do not usually use this very
        yellow latten as much because of the calamine which is heated. They cast red
            <material>copper</material> and turn it yellow with fresh <material>calamine</material>,
        or with some prepared tutty. Before casting, clean it with <material>charcoal</material>
        with a quere made of <material>copper</material> or <material>iron</material>. Then cover it
        with a cloth soaked in <material>lard</material> blended with
        <material>saltpetre</material>, or <material>sal ammoniac</material>, in order to protect it from wind, which
        would cool it down. </block>
</entry>
