<entry identifier="p142v_1">
  <folio number="142v" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f290.image"/>
  
  <annotations>
        <annotation url="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/0BwJi-u8sfkVDfkJmS2RybjBpTmpsVFhDQVo1RVZKMjRGY0d6QlNTYVhqS1VsYi13a0FkLUU" title="Too Thin Things"/>
  </annotations>
  
  <heading>Molding grasshoppers and things too thin</heading>
  <purpose type="making"/>
  <activity type="casting"/>
  <activity type="casting animals"/>
<activity type="casting things too thin"/>   
  <!-- <related-block>  -->
    <block purpose="making"> If you have to mold a piece of written-on paper that
          is too thin, after you have done the first cast and it has set, give
      a little thickness to the reverse of your paper with <material>melted butter</material>, which
      is the most appropriate means there is, &amp; for strengthening the wings of either a
      <animal>butterfly</animal> or a <animal>grasshopper</animal>, or any delicate part of an animal to which you need to
      give thickness. But take heed to apply this melted <material>butter</material> under the wing or
      in whichever place it will not be seen. For giving thickness to a <plant>pansy</plant> or other
      flowers, <material>butter</material> is not good, but rather <material>wheat oil</material>, which is
      soon dry &amp; holds firm. <material>Wax</material> would not be appropriate here for it is
      too hot once melted, and it makes the thing to which it is applied contract. But butter is
      amiable and handleable. </block>

  <block position="left-top" purpose="advice">If you write on <material>paper</material> or on common <material>carton</material> and your
      letters are made with <material>gum</material>, the moisture of the <tool>clay plate</tool>
      (?) or the wet (?) <material>sand</material> for a <material>noyau</material> will moisten
      your letters and undo them. Write therefore with <material>cinnabar</material> mixed with <material>oil</material>,
    on oiled &amp; stamped (?) <material>paper</material>. </block>
  <!-- </related-block>  -->

  <block position="left-middle" purpose="advice"> + Reheat your molds with
      <material>charcoal</material> firstly lit in the forge, so that the fire is not too hot and
    does not break the molds. And do not fire as strongly where the mold is thin as where it is
    thick. </block>

</entry>
