<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry identifier="p143r_1">

    <folio number="143r" url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f291.image"/>

    <heading>Moulding turtles and tortoises</heading>
    <purpose type="making"/>
    <activity type="casting animals"/>
    <block> The <animal>turtle</animal> the one that lives in water is more beautiful to mold because it has prettier
        scales and straight legs. And the <animal>tortoises</animal> have crooked ones. They eat a lot. To get ready
        to kill them, open their mouth and pass a long <tool>penknife</tool> through all the intestines. And then
        make it swallow some <material>vinegar</material> mixed with <material>spirits</material> or <material>urine</material>, as one does for <animal>snakes</animal>. It is
        necessary to mould them in several pieces, and even the back sometimes because the sides of
        certain ones are narrower than others and in this instance do not release from the cast. To
        make them die, you must not boil them, because they come apart, even the shell, in the hot
        water. They the shells come out better when hollowed because their great thickness spoils
        the mold. <animal>Turtles</animal> are more lively. The <animal>tortoises</animal> are leaner, slower, and more sleepy. If you
        scratch <animal>turtles</animal> on their shells, no matter how sleepy they are, they move; <animal>tortoises</animal> do not. </block>

    <block position="left-top"> They <animal>turtles</animal>/<animal>tortoises</animal> die rather quickly in <material>vinegar</material> mixed with a little <material>spirits</material>
        or <material>urine</material>, as with all other animals. </block>

    <block position="left-top"> They <animal>turtles</animal>/<animal>tortoises</animal> keep their eyes closed in the winter, and appear as dead,
        having been numbed by the cold. They hide in the earth or under balls of grain or warm
        manure, and survive only on the dampness of the earth. </block>

    <block position="left-middle"> You must not mold them too soon after they die because they are still stiff.
        But on the day after, you will be able to manipulate them and bend their legs as you wish. </block>

</entry>
