<entry identifier="p167r_1">
<folio
number="167r"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f339.image"/>

<heading>Mortars</heading>

<figure identifier="fig_p167r_1"
url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5QTU2dDJtWHU5Nmc"/>

<block><material>Mortars</material> are made of the best alloy of <material>"métal"</material> and the finest possible <material>rosette</material> so that they do not burst, that is to say one part "métal" and two [parts] fine rosette or <material>old caudron</material>, which is even better. Some of them are of <unit>fifteen or seventeen lb.</unit> and are loaded with <unit>two and a half lb.</unit> of <material>grain powder</material>, and they are put on common windows and doors. Others are of a weight of <unit>25 to 27 lb.</unit> and are loaded with <unit>eight lb.</unit> of <material>powder</material>. And in such a way, they are made according to the stress they have to resist. On the outside, they are all the same shape, but in the inside, they are made like a crucible</block>

figure identifier="fig_p167r_2"
url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5OUZCVWpfdmlzbWc"/>

<block>narrower on the inside of the bottom and getting wider towards the mouth. And this is to reinforce the bottom, given the quantity of <material>powder</material> they hold, and so that they do not burst. Those of <unit>4 s. lb.</unit> are eight lines thick at the bottom, and get thinner in the inside towards the opening, which is of 4 lines. They have <unit>xiii "poulsses"</unit> long and <unit>seven in diameter</unit> at the mouth and opening.</block>

<folio
number="167v"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f340.image"/>

<block>The ones weighing about <unit>27 lb.</unit> are <unit>ix "pousses" long</unit> and the mouth is <unit>6 [pousses]</unit> in diameter. At their bottom, they are <unit>6 "lignes"</unit> thick, and <unit>3 ["lignes"]</unit>for the mouth. The ones weighing <unit>17 lb</unit> are <unit>8 "poulsses"</unit> long and the mouth is <unit>five [poulsses]</unit>. They are all covered together, all the <material>forks</material>, <material>rods</material>, and tools which one uses, with a big <tool>canvas</tool> or big <tool>cloth</tool> so that they do not make any noise. It is good that they sit loaded for a while. After the <material>powder</material> has been put in, it is grinded very hard and then tightly pressed paper is put in, then a cake of well pressed <material>wax</material> and, on the wax, another slab of <material>cork<material>/ that fits in very snugly and that you have to force in. In this way, the powder remains well packed and gives much greater force, and if you wish, you can put on the cork slab one of <material>wood</material> pierced in the middle, if the mortar has a pierced bottom, which is believed to be the easiest and which makes a greater hole because it cannot recoil. And for these that have a pierced bottom, one must have a good gimlet to first make the hole so that the rod, which is made by the point of the gimlet, has before and without noise attached the mortar. And for these, one must cover the button, which is quite sharply filed, with waxed canvas, or add <material>wax</material> to it so that it completely plugs the hole in the bottom. But because the doors are sometimes iron and the <material>iron rods</material> cannot pierce it, an iron fork made like pincers and another iron stick made with three claws, like you see painted, are use. And in this way, the mortar stays in place well and is immediately steadied. The iron rods must come out of the mortar from every point made by the gimlet, namely by <unit>three or 4 finger lengths</unit>, which all enter in the door. When the mortars are placed, the touch-hole is filled with good powder and inserted in it is a feather shaft filled with tightly pressed powder and moistened with <material>vinegar</material>, or if needed, the powder is firmly pressed with the palms of the hands and, having wet it with some saliva, you shape it like a cocoon or</block>

<folio number="168r"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f341.image"/>

<figure identifier="fig_p168r_1"
position="left-top"
url="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9-oNrvWdlO5RUdzVWVNM3l6QVU"/>

<block>rod that we put into the touch-hole, and then, with a <material>rope</material> wrapped around the end of a <material>baston</material>, we ignite it and promptly retreat to take cover. The small mortars of <unit>16 or 17 lb.</unit> are attached promptly with a short, hooked rod made like a wimble, and if it is of a good alloy, we can ignite it by hand. It is done in this way for mortars of <unit>27 lb.</unit>, but then we only put <unit>three lb.</unit> of powder. The door really needs to be strong so as not to be blown off for <unit>seventeenth lb.</unit> mortars. Some people use little bells worn by oxen or mules as an door for the mortars. Others load two canons of <material>guns</material> and, with a <material>gimlet</material> and a string, tie them with the opening against the door. If the mortars are good and do not explode, they only recoil and cannot harm if one is next to them.</block>

<list>
<item>A is a <material>small rod<material>/, hooked like the hinge of a door and made as a <material>biron</material> on one end in order to quickly attach a small mortar with handles of fifteen or xvii lb. for a common door or window.</item>

<item>B is a <material>small mortar</material> with handles.</item>

<item>C is a <material>common mortar</material> of <unit>27 or 30 lb</unit>. pierced at the bottom, where a large iron rod passes, button-like on one end made like a biron on the tip so as to quickly hang the mortar against a door that will not be covered with iron plates.</item>

<item>D These are slabs of <material>wax</material>, <material>cork</material> and <material>wood</material> for loading the mortar and well packing the powder.</item>

<item>E <tool>iron fork</tool> made in the form of pincers as tall as a man, used to quickly set the mortar without a rod. It must be of soft iron so that the sides fold easily, if needed, and to accommodate the height or width of the door.</item>

<item>F is another <tool>iron fork</tool> of the same height that supports the fork made as pincers and also sustains the mortar, and with its low claw prevents the pincers from recoiling.</item>

<folio
number="168v"
url="http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10500001g/f342.image"/>

<item>G <material>mortar with handles</material> placed with its rod.</item>

<item>H knife-like <tool>saws</tool> to cut, if needed, a <tool>portcullis</tool>.</item>

<item>J the <tool>big iron rods</tool> that cross and tie the mortar.</item>

<item>K are like <tool>iron rods</tool>, all round and covered with cloths, like all the rest, so as to make the big iron rods, pierced close to the button, turn.</item>

<item>L <tool>axes</tool> that one must always carry to chop and to break, in the fortuitous case that the mortar has left anything entirely.</item>

<item>M a large wood <tool>mallet</tool> for knocking down what was begun and weakened by the axes and "birons".</item>

<item>N are big <tool>wheelwright augers</tool> and <tool>birons</tool> for easily cutting a door or window by making large holes close to one another.</item>

<item>O <material>crutches</material> as tall as a man that must be carried to put under a portcullis immediately after the canon has been shot and to prevent the portcullis from falling.</item>

<item>P are small <tool>iron pincers</tool> for putting any low mortar against the bolt of a door.</item>
</list>
</entry>